This is a good time to talk about how people commonly think about vectors as points.
趁这个机会 我们来谈谈为什么人们经常会把向量看作点
It gets really crowded to think about a whole collection of vectors, sitting on a line.
想象一下所有向量都位于一条直线上 是不是有些拥挤？
And more crowded still,
还有更拥挤的
to think about all two-dimensional vectors all at once filling up the plane.
想象所有二维向量同时出现 填满了整个平面
So when dealing with collections of vectors like this,
所以在处理这类向量集合时
it is common to represent each one with just a point in space.
我们通常会用空间里的一个点来表示一个向量
The point at the tip of that vector,
也就是向量头部所在的那个点
where as usual, I want you thinking about that vector with its tail on the origin.
和之前一样 我们默认向量的尾部在原点
That way, if you want to think about
这样一来 如果要研究
every possible vector whose tip sits on a certain line,
头部落在某一直线上的所有可能向量
just think about the line itself.
就只需考虑那条直线本身了
Likewise, to think about all possible two-dimensional vectors all at once,
同理 在研究所有可能的二维向量时
conceptualize each one as the point where its tip sits.
可以把每个向量看作其头部所在的点
So, in effect what you will be thinking about is
因此 你要考虑的其实是
the infinite flat sheet of two-dimensional space itself,
二维空间这个无限大的平面
leaving the arrows out of it.
如果把向量的箭头都去掉的话
In general, if you are thinking about a vector on its own, think of it as an arrow.
总地来说 如果你只研究一个向量 那就把向量想成一个箭头
And if you are dealing with a collection of vectors,
如果要研究向量集
it's convenient to think of them all as points.
那就将向量想成点
So, for our span example,
于是 在说到张成空间时
the span of most pairs of vectors ends up being
大多数向量对的张成空间
the entire infinite sheet of two-dimensional space.
其实就是二维空间那个无限大的平面
But if they line up, their span is just a line.
如果向量共线 那其张成空间就是一条直线
The idea of span gets a lot more interesting if we
一旦我们开始研究三维空间里的向量
start thinking about vectors in three-dimensional space.
张成空间这个概念就变得有趣多了
For example, if you take two vectors in 3D space,
举个例子 三维空间里
that are not pointing in the same direction.
两个方向不同的向量
What does it mean to take their span?
张成空间是怎么样的呢？
Well, their span is the collection of all possible linear combinations,
张成空间就是这两个向量
of those two vectors.
所有可能线性组合的集合
Meaning all possible vectors you get by
也就是
scaling each of the two of them in some way and then adding them together.
分别对这两个向量进行缩放并将结果相加 所得所有可能向量的集合
You can kind of imagine turning two different knobs to
你可以把这想成是旋转两个不同的旋钮
change the two scalars defining the linear combination,
以改变两个标量 定义不同的线性组合的过程
adding the scaled vectors and following the tip of the resulting vector.
将缩放后的向量相加 沿着所得向量的头部
That tip will trace out some kind of
会引申出某个平面
flat sheet cutting through the origin of three-dimensional space.
将原本的三维空间切成两半
This flat sheet is the span of the two vectors, or more precisely,
而这个平面就是这两个向量的张成空间 更准确地说
the set of all possible vectors whose tips sit
所有头部落在这个平面上的可能向量的集合
on that flat sheet is the span of your two vectors.
就是这两个向量的张成空间
Isn't that a beautiful mental image?
这么想象是不是很美呢？
So, what happens if we add a third vector
如果我们加入第三个向量
and consider the span of all three of those guys?
那这三个向量的张成空间又会是什么呢？
A linear combination of three vectors is
三个向量的线性组合
defined pretty much the same way as it is for two.
和两个向量的线性组合的定义很像
You'll choose three different scalars,
你需要选三个不同的标量
scale each of those vectors and then add them all together.
对各向量进行缩放 然后将缩放结果相加
And again, the span of these vectors is the set of all possible linear combinations.
同理 这些向量的张成空间就是所有可能线性组合的集合
Two different things could happen here.
此时会有两种情况
If your third vector happens to be sitting on the span of the first two,
如果第三个向量刚好落在前两个向量的张成空间上
then the span doesn't change.
那张成空间会保持不变
You're sort of trapped, on that same flat sheet.
有点像是你卡在同一平面上了
In other words, adding a scaled version of that third vector to
换句话说 在线性组合里添加经过缩放的第三个向量
the linear combination doesn't really give you access to any new vectors.
并不能得到任何新向量
But if you just randomly choose a third vector,
但如果你随机选出第三个向量
it's almost certainly not sitting on the span of those first two.
通常它都不会落在前两个向量的张成空间上
Then, since it is pointing in a separate direction,
由于第三个向量的方向与前两个不同
it unlocks access to every possible three-dimensional vector.
所以你可以借此访问所有可能的三维向量
One way I like to think about this,
我喜欢这么想
is that as you scale that new third vector,
在缩放第三个向量时
it moves around that span sheet of the first two sweeping it through all of space.
它会四处移动前两个向量的张成空间 使其抵达三维空间的任意位置
Another way to think about it,
也可以这么想
is that you are making full use of the three freely changing scalars that you
充分借助三个可自由变换的标量
have at your disposal to access the full three dimensions of space.
你就能访问三维空间的任意位置
Now, in the case where the third vector was already sitting on
如果第三个向量落在了前两个向量的张成空间上
the span of the first two or the case where two vectors happen to line up,
或是两个向量共线了
we want some terminology to describe the fact
我们有一个术语
that at least one of these vectors is redundant.
可以描述这种至少有一个向量冗余的情况
Not adding anything to our span.
此时张成空间不会有任何变化
Whenever this happens, where you have
无论什么时候
multiple vectors and you could remove one without reducing the span,
只要你有多个向量 而且可以在不减少张成空间的情况下删除其中一个向量
the relevant terminology is to say that they are linearly dependent.
那就可以说这些向量是线性相关的
Another way of phrasing that would be to say that one of
也就是说
the vectors can be expressed as a linear combination of the others,
其中一个向量可以用其它向量的线性组合来表示
since it is already in the span of the others.
因为该向量落在了其它向量的张成空间上
On the other hand, if each vector really does add another dimension to the span,
相反 如果每个向量都会增加张成空间的维度
they are said to be linearly independent.
那就说这些向量线性无关
So with all of that terminology and hopefully with some good mental images to go with it,
学会了这些术语 想来你也能充分想象相应的情况了
let me leave you with a puzzle before we go.
在继续往下讲之前 我们先来看一个问题
The technical definition of a basis of a space is
一个空间的基的科学定义是
a set of linearly independent vectors that span that space.
一个张成了该空间的线性无关的向量集合
Now given how I described a basis earlier and given
现在 请根据我之前对基的描述
your current understanding of the words span and linearly independent,
和你现在对张成空间和线性无关的理解
think about why this definition would make sense.
思考这个定义的意义
In the next video, I will get into matrices and transforming space. See you then.
下一个视频将讲解矩阵和空间变换 下个视频见